Finding Aid for James Karoub Papers, 1962-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James Karoub Papers 1962-1994
Karoub, James, 1929-1994.
1.5 linear ft.
0606 Aa 2
James Karoub was an Arab American lobbyist and legislator in Michigan. Most notably, he served in the Michigan House of Representatives and founded the successful Michigan lobbying firm, Karoub Associates. The Karoub papers consist of newspaper clippings and articles, correspondence, some campaign material, scrapbooks, photographs, and a sound recording.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Alice Karoub (donor no. 9678 ) in December 2005.
The collection is open to research.
James Karoub was an Arab American lobbyist and legislator in Michigan. He was the Democratic representative in the Michigan House from 1962 to 1963 and 1965 to 1968. He also was involved in local politics, serving as the police and fire commissioner of his hometown of Highland Park from 1959 to 1964. In 1968, he ran for the mayor of Highland Park. Despite winning the primary, the Michigan Supreme Court ruled (based on the Michigan Constitution) that he was ineligible to run because he was still serving in the House. In 1968, he founded Karoub Associates, "the oldest multi-client government relations firm in Michigan" (http://www.karoubassociates.com/about/index.htm). Karoub passed away in 1994.
The Karoub papers consist mainly of newspaper clippings and articles covering various aspects of Karoub's political career. Other papers include correspondence, some campaign material, documents from the Michigan Supreme Court case covering the mayoral controversy, and a few notes and speeches.
The collection also includes a scrapbook, photographs, and a sound recording. The photographs include portraits of Karoub, photographs of Karoub at different events, as well as photos of Karoub with various political figures, including G. Mennen Williams, George Romney, James J. Blanchard, and Hubert Humphrey. Karoub's farewell speech for mayor is also included in this collection.
Subjects:
Karoub, James, 1929-1994.; Legislators--Michigan.; Lobbyists--Michigan.; Arab Americans--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Karoub, James, 1929-1994.; Legislators--Michigan.; Lobbyists--Michigan.; Arab Americans--Michigan.; Governors--Michigan.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-; Romney, George W., 1907-; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Blanchard, James J., 1942-; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Scrapbooks.
- Topical
  - Campaign materials, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Certificates, 1966-1994 (Box 1)
  - Civil Service Commission (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1969, 1994 (Box 1)
  - House of Representatives material, 1965-1978 (Box 1)
  - Karoub Associates (Box 1)
  - Mayor controversy, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper articles
    - 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1968, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1969-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - Lobbying, etc. (Box 1)
  - Notes and speeches, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    (include portraits, photos of Karoub as part of group at signing of bills by governors George Romney and William Milliken; photos of Karoub with other public figures such as Hubert Humphrey and James Blanchard)
  - Scrapbook, 1964-1979 (Box 2)
  - Sound Recording: Farewell speech for mayor, 1968, 1 1/2" reel (Box 2)